<chapter id="introduction">
    <title>Introduction</title>
    
    <para>This document defines the syntax and semantics of the Ceylon language.
    The intended audience includes compiler implementors, interested parties
    who wish to contribute to the evolution of the language, and experienced 
    developers seeking a precise definition of language constructs. However, in
    light of the newness of the language, we will begin with an overview of the
    main features of the language and SDK. A brief introduction to programming 
    in the language may be found at the following address:</para>
    
    <programlisting>http://ceylon-lang.org/documentation/tour/</programlisting>
    
    <section id="languageoverview">
        <title>Language overview</title>
    
        <para>
        Ceylon is a general-purpose programming  language featuring a syntax similar 
        to Java and C#. It is imperative, statically-typed, block-structured, 
        object-oriented, and higher-order. By <emphasis>statically-typed</emphasis>, 
        we mean that the compiler performs extensive type checking, with the help of 
        type annotations that appear in the code. By <emphasis>object-oriented</emphasis>, 
        we mean that the language supports user-defined types and features a nominative 
        type system where a type is a set of named attributes and operations, and that 
        it supports inheritance and subtype polymorphism. By <emphasis>higher-order</emphasis>, 
        we mean that every referenceable program element (every attribute, every 
        operation, and every type) is also a value. By <emphasis>block-structured</emphasis>, 
        we mean to say that the language features lexical scoping and an extremely 
        regular recursive syntax for declarations and statements.
        </para>
        
        <para>
        Ceylon improves upon the Java language and type system to reduce verbosity 
        and increase typesafety compared to Java and C#. Ceylon encourages a more 
        functional, somewhat less imperative style of programming, resulting in code 
        which is easier to reason about, and easier to refactor. 
        </para>
        
        <section id="runtimeandplatform">
            <title>Runtime and platform</title>
        
            <para>
            Ceylon programs execute in any standard Java Virtual Machine or on any
            JavaScript virtual machine, and take advantage of the memory management and 
            concurrency features of the virtual machine in which they execute. Ceylon
            programs are packaged into <emphasis>modules</emphasis> with well-defined
            inter-module dependencies, and always execute inside a runtime environment 
            with module isolation.
            </para>
            
            <para>
            The Ceylon compiler is able to compile Ceylon code that calls Java classes or 
            interfaces, and Java code that calls Ceylon classes or interfaces. JavaScript
            code is able to interact with Ceylon classes and functions compiled to JavaScript. 
            Via a special <emphasis>dynamic</emphasis> mode, code written in Ceylon may call
            functions defined natively in JavaScript.
            </para>
            
            <para>
            Moreover, Ceylon provides its own native SDK as a replacement for the Java 
            platform class libraries. Certain SDK modules depend upon services available
            only on the Java platform. Other SDK modules, including the core 
            <emphasis>language module</emphasis>, are cross-platform and may also be used 
            in a JavaScript virtual machine.
            </para>
            
        </section>
    
    </section>

    <section id="thetypesystem">
        <title>Type system</title>
        
        <para>
        Ceylon, like Java and C#, features a hybrid type system with both subtype 
        polymorphism and parameteric polymorphism. A type is either a stateless 
        <emphasis>interface</emphasis>, a stateful <emphasis>class</emphasis>, a 
        <emphasis>type parameter</emphasis>, or a <emphasis>union</emphasis> or 
        <emphasis>intersection</emphasis> of other types. A class, interface, or 
        type parameter may be defined as a subtype of another type. A class or 
        interface may declare type parameters, which abstract the definition of the 
        class or interface over all types which may be substituted for the type 
        parameters.
        </para>
        
        <para>
        Like C#, and unlike Java, Ceylon's type system is fully reified. In 
        particular, generic type arguments are reified, eliminating many problems 
        that result from type erasure in Java.
        </para>
        
        <para>
        There are no primitive types or arrays in Ceylon&mdash;every Ceylon type can 
        be represented within the language itself. So all values are instances of the 
        type hierarchy root <literal>Anything</literal>, which is a class. However, 
        the Ceylon compiler is permitted to optimize certain code to take advantage 
        of the optimized performance of primitive types on the Java or JavaScript VM.
        </para>
        
        <para>
        Furthermore, all types inferred or even computed internally by the Ceylon 
        compiler are expressible within the language itself. Within the type system,
        <emphasis>non-denoteable</emphasis> types simply do not arise. The type system 
        is based upon computation of <emphasis>principal types</emphasis>. There is no 
        way to construct an expression which does not have a unique principal type 
        expressible within the language. The principal type of an expression is a 
        subtype of all other types to which the expression could be soundly assigned.
        </para>
        
        <section id="mixininheritance">
            <title>Mixin inheritance</title>
            
            <para>
            Ceylon supports a restricted form of multiple inheritance, often called 
            <emphasis>mixin inheritance</emphasis>. A class must extend exactly one other 
            class. But a class or interface may satisfy (extend or implement) an arbitrary 
            number of interfaces.
            </para>
            
            <para>
            Classes hold state and define logic to initialize that state when the class is 
            instantiated. A concrete class is a class that contains only concrete member 
            definitions. Concrete classes may be directly instantiated. An abstract class 
            may contain formal member declarations. Abstract classes may not be instantiated.
            </para>
            
            <para>
            Interfaces may define concrete members, but may not hold state (references to 
            other objects) or initialization logic. This restriction helps eliminate the 
            problems traditionally associated with multiple inheritance. Ceylon never 
            performs any kind of "linearization" of the supertypes of a type. Interfaces 
            may not be directly instantiated.
            </para>
        
        </section>
        
        <section id="algrebraictypesselftypes">
            <title>Algebraic types, self types, and type families</title>
            
            <para>
            Ceylon does not feature Java-style enumerated types as a first-class construct. 
            Instead, any abstract type may specify its <emphasis>cases</emphasis>&mdash;an
            enumerated list of instances and/or subtypes. This facility is used to simulate 
            both enumerated types and functional-style "algebraic" (sum) types. 
            </para>
            
            <programlisting>interface Identity of Person | Organization { ... }</programlisting>
            
            <para>
            A closely related feature is support for <emphasis>self types</emphasis> and 
            <emphasis>type families</emphasis>. A self type is a type parameter of an 
            abstract type (like <literal>Comparable</literal>) which represents the type of 
            a concrete instantiation (like <literal>String</literal>) of the abstract type,
            within the definition of the abstract type itself. In a type family, the self 
            type of a type is declared not by the type itself, but by a containing type 
            which groups together a set of related types.
            </para>
            
        </section>
        
        <section id="simplifiedgenerics">
            <title>Simplified generics</title>
            
            <para>
            Ceylon does not support Java-style wildcard type parameters, raw types, or any 
            other kind of existential type. And the Ceylon compiler never even uses any kind 
            of "non-denotable" type to reason about the type system. So generics-related 
            error messages are understandable to humans.
            </para>
            
            <para>
            Instead of wildcard types, Ceylon features <emphasis>declaration-site variance</emphasis>. 
            A type parameter may be marked as covariant or contravariant by the class or 
            interface that declares the parameter.
            </para>
            
            <para>
            Ceylon has a somewhat more expressive system of generic type constraints with 
            a cleaner, more regular syntax. The syntax for declaring constraints on a type 
            parameter looks very similar to a class or interface declaration. Ceylon supports 
            upper bound type constraints and also <emphasis>enumerated bounds</emphasis>.
            </para>
            
            <programlisting>interface Producer&lt;out Value, in Rate&gt; 
        given Value satisfies Object 
        given Rate of Float|Decimal { ... }</programlisting>
        
        </section>
        
        <section id="unionandintersectiontypes">
            <title>Union and intersection types</title>
        
            <para>
            A <emphasis>union type</emphasis>, for example <literal>String|Number</literal>, 
            or <emphasis>intersection type</emphasis>, for example 
            <literal>Identifiable&amp;List&lt;String&gt;</literal>, may be formed from 
            two or more types defined elsewhere. 
            </para>
            
            <para>
            Union types make it possible to write code that operates polymorphically 
            over types defined in disparate branches of the type heirarchy without the 
            need for intermediate adaptor classes. Intersection types make it possible 
            to operate polymorphically over all subtypes of a list of types. Union and
            intersection types provide some of the benefits of structural ("duck") 
            typing, within the confines of a nominative type system, and therefore 
            certain Ceylon idioms are reminiscent of code written in dynamically-typed
            languages.  
            </para>
                
            <para>
            Union and intersection types play a central role in generic type argument 
            inference and therefore underly the whole system of principal typing. For
            example, the following expression has type 
            <literal>HashMap&lt;String,Integer|Float&gt;</literal>:
            </para>
            
            <programlisting>HashMap { "float"->0.0, "integer"->0 }</programlisting>
        
        </section>
        
        <section id="typealiasesandtypeinference">   
            <title>Type aliases and type inference</title>
            
            <para>    
            Type aliases and type inference help reduce the verbosity of code which 
            uses generic types, eliminating the need to repeatedly specify generic
            type arguments.
            </para>
        
            <para>
            A <emphasis>type alias</emphasis> is similar to a C-style <literal>typedef</literal>.
            </para>
            
            <programlisting>interface Strings =&gt; Sequence&lt;String&gt;;</programlisting>
            <programlisting>alias Number =&gt; Integer|Float|Whole|Decimal;</programlisting>
            
            <para>
            Local <emphasis>type inference</emphasis> allows a type annotation to be
            eliminated altogether. The type of a block-local value or function is 
            inferred from its definition if the keyword <literal>value</literal> or 
            <literal>function</literal> occurs in place of the type declaration.
            </para>
            
            <programlisting>value name = person.name;</programlisting>
            <programlisting>function sqrt(Float x) => x^0.5;</programlisting>
            
            <para>
            The type of a control-structure variable also may be inferred.
            </para>
            
            <programlisting>for (n in 0..max) { ... }</programlisting>
            <!--programlisting>try (tx = Transaction()) { ... }</programlisting-->
            
            <para>
            Ceylon features an especially elegant approach to generic type argument 
            inference, making it possible to instantiate container types, even 
            inhomogoneous container types, without the need to explicitly mention any 
            types at all.  
            </para>
            
            <programlisting>value numbers = { -1, 0, -1, -1.0, 0.0, 1.0 };</programlisting>
            
            <para>
            By limiting type inference to local declarations, Ceylon ensures that all 
            types may be inferred by the compiler in a single pass of the source code. 
            Type inference works in the "downward" and "outward" directions. The compiler 
            is able to determine the type of an expression without considering the rest 
            of the statement or declaration in which it appears.
            </para>
            
        </section>
        
        <section id="metaprogramming">
            <title>Metaprogramming</title>
            
            <para>
            Ceylon provides sophisticated support for meta-programming, including program
            element <emphasis>annotations</emphasis>, a typesafe <emphasis>metamodel</emphasis>, 
            and <emphasis>events</emphasis>. Generic code may invoke members reflectively 
            and intercept member invocations. This facility is more powerful, and much more 
            typesafe, than reflection in Java.
            </para>
        
        </section>
        
    </section>
        
    <section id="objectorientedprogramming">
        <title>Object-oriented programming</title>
        
        <para>The primary unit of organization of an object-oriented program is
        the class. But Ceylon, unlike Java, doesn't require that <emphasis>every</emphasis> 
        function or value belong to a class. It's perfectly normal to program 
        with a mix of classes and toplevel functions. Contrary to popular belief, 
        this does not make the program less object-oriented. A function is, after 
        all, an object.</para>
    
        <section id="initializationandinstantiation">
            <title>Class initialization and instantiation</title>
            
            <para>
            Ceylon does not feature any Java-like constructor declaration and so each 
            Ceylon class has a parameter list, and exactly one 
            <emphasis>initializer</emphasis>&mdash;the body of the class. This helps
            reduce verbosity and results in a more regular block structure.
            </para>
            
            <programlisting>class Point(Float x, Float y) { ... }</programlisting>
            
            <para>
            The Ceylon compiler guarantees that the value of any attribute of a class 
            is initialized before it is used in an expression.
            </para>
            
            <para>
            A class may be a member of an outer class. Such a member class may be 
            refined (overridden) by a subclass of the outer class. Instantiation is 
            therefore a polymorphic operation in Ceylon, eliminating the need for a 
            factory method in some circumstances.
            </para>
            
            <para>
            Ceylon provides a streamlined syntax for defining an anonymous class which 
            is only instantiated in exactly the place it is defined. Among other uses,
            the <literal>object</literal> declaration is useful for creating singleton 
            objects or method-local interface implementations. 
            </para>
            
            <programlisting>object origin extends Point(0.0, 0.0) {}</programlisting>
        
        </section>
        
       <section id="methodsandattributes">
            <title>Functions, methods, values, and attributes</title>
            
            <para><emphasis>Functions</emphasis> and <emphasis>values</emphasis> are 
            the bread and butter of programming. Ceylon functions are similar to Java 
            methods, except that they don't need to belong to a class. Ceylon values 
            are polymorphic, and abstract their internal representation, similar to 
            C# properties.</para>
            
            <programlisting>String name =&gt; firstName + " " + lastName;</programlisting>
            
            <para>The Ceylon compiler guarantees that any value is initialized before 
            it is used in an expression.</para>
            
            <para>
            A function belonging to a type is called a <emphasis>method</emphasis>. 
            A value belonging to a type is called an <emphasis>attribute</emphasis>.  
            There are no <literal>static</literal> members. Instead, 
            <emphasis>toplevel</emphasis> functions and values are declared as direct 
            members of a package. This, along with certain other features, gives the 
            language a more regular block structure.
            </para>
            
            <para>
            By default, an attribute or value may not be assigned a new value after
            its initial value has been specified. Mutable attributes and variable 
            values must be explicitly declared using the <literal>variable</literal> 
            annotation.
            </para>
            
            <para>
            Ceylon does not support function overloading. Each method of a type has a 
            distinct name.
            </para>
        
        </section>
        
        <section id="defaultparameters">
            <title>Defaulted parameters and variadic parameters</title>
            
            <para>
            Instead of method and constructor overloading, Ceylon supports parameters 
            with default values and <emphasis>variadic</emphasis> parameters.
            </para>
            
            <programlisting>void addItem(Product product, Integer quantity=1) { ... }</programlisting>
            
            <programlisting>String join(String* strings) { ... }</programlisting>
            
            <para>
            Furthermore, a generic method may be used to emulate parameter type 
            overloading.
            </para>
            
            <programlisting>Number sum&lt;Number&gt;(Number* numbers) given Number of Integer | Float { ... }</programlisting>
            
            <para>Therefore, a single method in Ceylon may emulate the signatures of 
            several overloaded methods in Java.</para>
        
        </section>
        
        <section id="firstclassfunctions">
            <title>First-class functions and higher-order programming</title>
            
            <para>
            Ceylon supports first-class function types and higher-order functions, with 
            minimal extensions to the traditional C syntax. A function declaration may 
            specify a <emphasis>callable parameter</emphasis> that accepts references to 
            other functions with a certain signature. 
            </para>
            
            <programlisting>String find(Boolean where(String string)) { ... }</programlisting>
            
            <para>
            The argument of such a callable parameter may be either a reference to a 
            named function declared elsewhere, or a new function defined inline as part 
            of the method invocation. A function may even return an invocable reference 
            to another function.
            </para>
            
            <programlisting>value result = { "C", "Java", "Ceylon" }.find((String s) =&gt; s.size>1);</programlisting>
            
            <!--programlisting>value matches = { "", "hello", "world" }.filter((String s) =&gt; nonempty s);</programlisting-->
            
            <para>
            The type of a function is expressed within the type system as an 
            instantiation of the interface <literal>Callable</literal>. The parameter 
            types are expressed as a tuple type. So the type of the function 
            <literal>(String s) =&gt; s.size>1</literal> is 
            <literal>Callable&lt;Boolean,[String]&gt;</literal>, which may be 
            abbreviated to <literal>Boolean(String)</literal>.
            </para>
            
            <para>
            Methods and attributes may also be used as functions.
            </para>
        
            <programlisting>value names = people.map(Person.name);</programlisting>
            
            <programlisting>value values = keys.map(keyedValues.get);</programlisting>
            
        
        </section>
        
        <section id="namingconventionsandannotations">
            <title>Naming conventions, annotations, and inline documentation</title>
            
            <para>
            The Ceylon compiler enforces the traditional Smalltalk naming convention:
            type names begin with an initial uppercase letter&mdash;for example, 
            <literal>Liberty</literal> or <literal>RedWine</literal>&mdash;member names 
            and local names with an initial lowercase letter or underscore&mdash;for
            example, <literal>blonde</literal>, <literal>immanentize()</literal> or 
            <literal>boldlyGo()</literal>.
            </para> 
            
            <para>
            This restrictions allows a much cleaner syntax for program element 
            annotations than the syntax found in either Java or C#. Declaration 
            "modifiers" like <literal>shared</literal>, <literal>abstract</literal>, 
            and <literal>variable</literal> aren't keywords in Ceylon, they're ordinary 
            annotations.
            </para>
            
            <programlisting>"Base type for higher-order abstract stuff."
shared abstract class AbstractMetaThingy() { ... }</programlisting>
            
            <para>
            The documentation compiler reads inline documentation specified 
            using the <literal>doc</literal> annotation.
            </para>
        
        </section>
        
        <section id="structureddata">
            <title>Named arguments and tree-like structures</title>
            
            <para>
            Ceylon's named argument lists provide an elegant means of initializing objects 
            and collections. The goal of this facility is to replace the use of XML for 
            expressing hierarchical structures such as documents, user interfaces, 
            configuration and serialized data.
            </para>
            
            <programlisting>Html page = Html {
    Head { 
        title="Hello"; 
    };
    Body { 
        P {
            css = "greeting"; 
            "Hello, World!" 
        }; 
    };
}</programlisting>
            
            <para>
            An especially important application of this facility is Ceylon's built-in 
            support for program element annotations.
            </para>
        
        </section>
        
        <section id="modularity">
            <title>Modularity</title>
            
            <para>
            Toplevel declarations are organized into <emphasis>packages</emphasis> and 
            <emphasis>modules</emphasis>. Ceylon features language-level access control 
            via the <literal>shared</literal> annotation which can be used to express 
            block-local, package-private, module-private, and public visibility for 
            a program element. There's no equivalent to Java's <literal>protected</literal>.
            </para>
            
            <para>A module corresponds to a versioned packaged archive. Its 
            <emphasis>module descriptor</emphasis> expresses its dependencies to other
            modules. The tooling and execution model for the language is based around 
            modularity and module archives.</para>
        
        </section>
    
    </section>
    
    <section id="thelanguagemodule">
        <title>Language module</title>
        
        <para>The Ceylon language module defines a set of built-in types which form 
        the basis for several powerful features of the language. The following 
        functionality is defined as syntactic "sugar" that makes it easier and more 
        convenient to interact with the language module.</para>
    
        <section id="operatorsandoperatorpolymorphism">
            <title>Operators and operator polymorphism</title>
            
            <para>
            Ceylon features a rich set of operators, including most of the operators 
            supported by C and Java. True operator overloading is not supported. 
            However, each operator is defined to act upon a certain class or interface 
            type, allowing application of the operator to any class which extends or 
            satisfies that type. For example, the <literal>+</literal> operater may be
            applied to any class that satisfies the interface <literal>Summable</literal>. 
            This approach is called <emphasis>operator polymorphism</emphasis>.
            </para>
        
        </section>
        
        <section id="numerictypes">
            <title>Numeric and character types</title>
            
            <para>Ceylon's numeric type system is much simpler than C, C# or Java, with
            exactly two built-in numeric types (compared to six in Java and eleven in 
            C#). The built-in types are classes representing integers and floating point 
            numbers. <literal>Integer</literal> and <literal>Float</literal> values are 
            64 bit by default, and may be optimized for 32 bit architectures via use of 
            the <literal>small</literal> annotation.</para>
            
            <para>The module <literal>ceylon.math</literal> provides two additonal
            numeric types representing arbitrary precision integers and arbitrary 
            precision decimals.</para>
            
            <para>Ceylon has <literal>Character</literal> and <literal>String</literal>
            classes, and, unlike Java or C#, every character is a full 32-bit Unicode
            codepoint. Conveniently, a <literal>String</literal> is a 
            <literal>List&lt;Character&gt;</literal>.</para>
        
        </section>
        
        <section id="compiletimesafety">
            <title>Compile-time safety for optional values and type narrowing</title>
            
            <para>
            There is no primitive null in Ceylon. The null value is an instance of 
            the class <literal>Null</literal> that is not assignable to user-defined 
            class or interface types. An <emphasis>optional type</emphasis> is a 
            union type like <literal>Null|String</literal>, which may be abbreviated
            to <literal>String?</literal>. An optional type is not assignable to a 
            non-optional type except via use of the special-purpose 
            <literal>if (exists ... )</literal> construct. Thus, the Ceylon compiler 
            is able to detect illegal use of a null value at compile time. Therefore, 
            there is no equivalent to Java's <literal>NullPointerException</literal> 
            in Ceylon.
            </para>
            
            <para>
            Similarly, there are no C-style typecasts in Ceylon. Instead, the 
            <literal>if (is ... )</literal> and <literal>case (is ... )</literal> 
            constructs may be used to narrow the type of an object reference without 
            risk of a <literal>ClassCastException</literal>. The combination of
            <literal>case (is ... )</literal> with algebraic types amounts to a kind
            of language-level support for the visitor pattern.
            </para>
            
            <para>
            Alternatively, <emphasis>type assertions</emphasis>, written 
            <literal>assert (is ... )</literal> or <literal>assert (exists ... )</literal>
            may be used to narrow the type of a reference.
            </para>
        
        </section>
        
        <section id="iterableobjectsandcomprehensions">
            <title>Iterable objects and comprehensions</title>
            
            <para>The interface <literal>Iterable</literal> represents a stream of
            values, which might be evaluated lazily. This interface is of central
            importance in the language module, and so the language provides a
            syntactic abbreviation for the type of an iterable object. The 
            abbreviation <literal>{String*}</literal> means 
            <literal>Iterable&lt;String&gt;</literal>. There is a convenient syntax
            for instantiating an iterable object, given a list of values:</para>
            
            <programlisting>{String*} words = {"hello", "world", "goodbye"};</programlisting>
            
            <para>A <emphasis>nonempty iterable</emphasis> is an iterable object
            which always produces at least one value. A nonempty iterabe type is
            written <literal>{String+}</literal>. Distingushing nonempty streams
            of values lets us correctly express the type of functions like
            <literal>max()</literal>:</para>
            
            <programlisting>{Float+} oneOrMore = .... ;
{Float*} zeroOrMore = .... ;
Float maxOfOneOrMore = max(oneOrMore); //never null
Float? maxOfZeroOrMore = max(zeroOrMore); //might be null</programlisting>
            
            <para><emphasis>Comprehensions</emphasis> are an expressive syntax for
            filtering and transforming streams of values. For example, they may be 
            used when instantiating an iterable object or collection:</para>
            
            <programlisting>value adults = { for (p in people) if (p.age>18) p.name };</programlisting>
            <programlisting>value peopleByName = HashMap { for (p in people) p.name->p };</programlisting>
            
            <para>Comprehensions are evaluated lazily.</para>
            
        </section>
        
        <section id="sequencesandtuples">
            <title>Sequences and tuples</title>
            
            <para><emphasis>Sequences</emphasis> are Ceylon's version of arrays. 
            However, the <literal>Sequential</literal> interface does not provide 
            operations for mutating the elements of the sequence&mdash;sequences
            are considered immutable. Because this interface is so useful, a type 
            like <literal>Sequential&lt;String&gt;</literal> may be abbreviated to 
            <literal>[String*]</literal>, or, for the sake of tradition, to 
            <literal>String[]</literal>.</para>
            
            <para>A <emphasis>nonempty sequence</emphasis> is a kind of sequence
            which always has at least one element. A nonempty sequence type is 
            written <literal>[String+]</literal>. The special-purpose 
            <literal>if (nonempty ... )</literal> construct narrows a sequence 
            type to a nonempty sequence type.</para>
            
            <para><emphasis>Tuples</emphasis> are a kind of sequence where the 
            type of each element is encoded into the static type of the tuple.
            <literal>Tuple</literal> is just an ordinary class in Ceylon, but 
            syntactic abbreviations let us write down tuple types in using a 
            streamlined syntax. For example, <literal>[Float,Float]</literal>
            is a pair of <literal>Float</literal>s. There is also a convenient 
            syntax for instantiating tuples and accessing their elements.</para>
            
            <programlisting>[Float,Float] origin = [0.0, 0.0];
Float x = origin[0];
Float y = origin[1];
Null z = origin[2]; //only two elements!</programlisting>
            
        </section>
    
    </section>
    
</chapter>
