<chapter id="modulesystem">
    <title>Module system</title>
    
    <para>The Ceylon module architecture enables a toolset which relieves 
    developers of many mundane tasks. The module system specifies:</para>
    
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para>the format of packaged deployable module archives (for
            the Java platform), module scripts (for the JavaScript platform), 
            and source archives,</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>the layout of a module repository</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>the format of the package descriptor files which contain
            information about the packages contained in a module, including
            whether a package is visible to other modules, and</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>the format of the module descriptor file which contains
            information about a module, along with a list of its
            versioned dependencies.</para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    
    <para>Thus, developers are never exposed to individual <literal>.class</literal>
    files, and are not required to manually manage module archives using the 
    operating system file manager. Instead, the toolset helps automate the 
    management of modules within module repositories.</para>
    
    <para>Circular dependencies between modules are not supported. The
    Ceylon compiler detects such dependencies and produces an error.</para>

    <section id="moduleruntime">
        <title>The module runtime and module isolation</title>
        
        <para>At any time, there may be multiple versions of a certain module 
        available in the virtual machine. Modules execute under the control of 
        the <emphasis>module runtime</emphasis>. The module runtime:</para>
        
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>obtains modules from module repositories,</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>reads module metadata and recursively loads 
                dependencies, and</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>isolates modules that belong to different
                assemblies.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        
        <para>Execution of a module begins with a specified toplevel method or 
        class, or with an entry point specified in the module descriptor, and 
        imported modules are loaded lazily as classes they contain are needed. 
        The name and version id of the imported module containing the needed 
        class are determined from the imported package name specified by the 
        compilation unit and the imported module version specified by the 
        module descriptor.</para>
                
        <para>The mechanism behind this is platform-dependent.</para>
        
        <section id="classloaders">
            <title>Module isolation for the Java platform</title>
        
            <para>In the JVM environment, Each version of each module is loaded 
            using a different class loader. Classes inside a module have access 
            to other classes in the same module and to classes belonging to 
            modules that are explicitly imported in the module descriptor. 
            Classes in other modules are not accessible.</para>
            
            <para>Ceylon supports a simplified class loader architecture:</para>
            
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The <emphasis>bootstrap</emphasis> class loader owns
                    classes required to bootstrap the module runtime. It is the
                    direct parent of all module class loaders, and its classes
                    are visible to all module class loaders.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>A <emphasis>module</emphasis> class loader owns classes
                    belonging to a given version of a certain module. Its classes
                    are visible only to classes belonging to the module class 
                    loader of a module which declares an explicit dependency on 
                    the given version of the first module.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            
            <comment><para>The Ceylon module runtime for the JVM is implemented
            using JBoss Modules. It is included in the Ceylon SDK.</para></comment>
        
        </section>
        
        <section id="requirejs">
            <title>Module isolation for the JavaScript platform</title>
            
            <para>In the JavaScript environment, modules are loaded using
            the <literal>require()</literal> function defined by CommonJS 
            Modules.</para>
            
            <comment><para>There are various implementations of the CommonJS-style 
            <literal>require()</literal> function, and Ceylon module scripts should
            work with any of them.</para></comment>
        
        </section>
        
        <section id="assemblies">
            <title>Assemblies</title>
            
            <comment><para>A future release of the language will add support for
            assemblies, that is, the ability to:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>package together several interdependent versioned modules 
                    into a single archive for deployment as a single well-defined 
                    application or service,</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>specify the name and version of the application or 
                    service, and</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>override the versions of imported modules declared in 
                    <literal>modules.ceylon</literal>, as defined in 
                    <xref linkend="moduledescriptors"/>, with assembly-specific
                    module versions.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para>An assembly archive will probably just be an archived module
            repository with an assembly descriptor.</para>
            </comment>
            
        </section>
        
    </section>

    <section id="sourcelayout">
        <title>Source layout</title>
        
        <para>A <emphasis>source directory</emphasis> contains Ceylon source 
        code in files with the extension <literal>.ceylon</literal> and Java 
        source code in files with the extension <literal>.java</literal>. 
        The module and package to which a compilation unit belongs is 
        determined by the subdirectory in which the source file is found.</para>
        
        <para>The name of the package to which a compilation unit belongs is 
        formed by replacing every path directory separator character with a 
        period in the relative path from the root source directory to the 
        subdirectory containing the source file. In the case of a Java source 
        file, the subdirectory must agree with the package specified by the 
        Java <literal>package</literal> declaration.</para>
        
        <para>The name of the module to which a compilation unit belongs is 
        determined by searching all containing directories for a module 
        descriptor. The name of the module is formed by replacing every path
        directory separator character with a period in the relative path 
        from the source directory to the subdirectory containing the module 
        descriptor. If no module descriptor is found, the code belongs to
        the <emphasis>default module</emphasis>.</para>
        
        <comment><para>Note: the default module is intended only as a 
        convenience for experimental code.</para></comment>
        
        <para>A package or compilation unit may belong to only one module.
        No more than one module descriptor may occur in the containing
        directories of a compilation unit.</para> 
        
        <para>Thus, the structure of the source directory containing the 
        module <literal>org.hello</literal> might be the following:</para>
        
        <programlisting><![CDATA[source/
    org/
        hello/
            module.ceylon      //the module descriptor
            main/
                hello.ceylon
            default/
                DefaultHello.ceylon
            personalized/
                PersonalizedHello.ceylon]]></programlisting>
                
        <para>The source code for multiple modules may be contained in a
        single source directory.</para>
                
    </section>
    
    <section id="modules">
        <title>Module architecture</title>
    
        <para>Compiled code is automatically packaged into <emphasis>module
        archives</emphasis> and <emphasis>module scripts</emphasis> by the 
        Ceylon compiler. A <emphasis>module repository</emphasis> is a 
        repository containing module archives, module scripts, and other
        miscellaneous artifacts. A module archive or module script is 
        automatically obtained from a module repository when code belonging 
        to the module is needed by the compiler or module runtime.</para>
        
        <para>Modules that form part of the Ceylon SDK are found in the
        module repository in the <literal>modules</literal> directory of 
        the Ceylon distribution.</para>
        
        <para>Red Hat maintains a central module repository at 
        <literal>http://modules.ceylon-lang.org</literal>. Read access to 
        this site is free of registration and free of charge. Ceylon projects 
        may apply for a user account which provides write access to the central 
        module repository.</para>
        
        <para>A module belonging to the central module repository must
        satisfy the following regulations:</para>
        
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>the first element of the module name must be a top-level
                internet domain name, and the second element of the module name 
                must be a second-level domain of the given top-level domain 
                owned by the organization distributing the module, and.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>the module must be made available under a royalty-free 
                license.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        
        <para>For example, a module developed by Red Hat might be named
        <literal>org.jboss.server</literal>.</para>
        
        <comment><para>TODO: should we require that module archives be signed 
        using the Java <literal>jarsigner</literal> tool?</para></comment>
        
        <section id="modulenamesandversionidentifiers">
            <title>Module names and version identifiers</title>
            
            <para>A module <emphasis>name</emphasis> is a period-separated
            list of lowercase identifiers, for example:</para>
            
            <screen>ceylon.language</screen>
            <screen>org.hibernate</screen>
            
            <para>It is recommended that module names follow the Java package
            naming convention embedding the organization's domain name (in
            this case, <literal>hibernate.org</literal>). The namespace
            <literal>ceylon</literal> is reserved for Ceylon SDK modules. The 
            namespace <literal>java</literal> is reserved for modules 
            belonging to the Java SDK. The namespace <literal>default</literal>
            is reserved for the default module.</para>
            
            <para>It is highly recommended, but not required, that every 
            user-written module have at least three identifiers in its name. 
            Therefore, <literal>org.hibernate.orm</literal> is strongly
            preferred to <literal>org.hibernate</literal>.</para>
            
            <para>Modules may not be "nested". That is, the list of identifiers 
            forming the name of a module may not be a prefix of the list of 
            identifiers forming the name of another module.</para>
            
            <para>A package belongs to a module if the list of identifiers 
            forming the name of the module is a prefix of the list of 
            identifiers forming the name of the package. For example, the 
            packages:</para>
            
            <screen>ceylon.language</screen>
            <screen>ceylon.language.assertion</screen>
            <screen>ceylon.language.meta</screen>
            <screen>ceylon.language.meta.declaration</screen>
            
            <para>belong to the module <literal>ceylon.language</literal>. The 
            packages:</para>
            
            <screen>org.hibernate</screen>
            <screen>org.hibernate.impl</screen>
            <screen>org.hibernate.cache</screen>
            
            <para>belong to the module <literal>org.hibernate</literal>.</para>
            
            <comment><para>TODO: This might not work out all that well in practice, 
            unless we introduce some additional convention for "extras" modules,
            for example, modules containing examples. It could be 
            <literal>org.hibernate</literal> vs <literal>org.hibernate_example</literal>
            or <literal>org.hibernate.core</literal> vs 
            <literal>org.hibernate.example</literal>.</para></comment>
    
            <para>The name of the default module is <literal>default</literal>. The 
            default module has no version and cannot be published to a remote repository 
            nor to the local repository cache under <filename>~/.ceylon/repo</filename>.</para>
            
            <para>A module <emphasis>version identifier</emphasis> is a character 
            string containing digits, periods, and lowercase letters, for example:</para>
            
            <screen>1.0.1</screen>
            <screen>3.0.0.beta</screen>
            
            <comment><para>TODO: at some stage we will probably need to add a format
            for specifying version ranges.</para></comment>
        
        </section>
        
        <section id="modulearchivenamesjava">
            <title>Module archive names for the Java platform</title>
        
            <para>A <emphasis>module archive name</emphasis> is constructed from 
            the module name and version identifier. A module archive name is of 
            the following standard form:</para>
            
            <synopsis><emphasis>&lt;module&gt;</emphasis>-<emphasis>&lt;version&gt;</emphasis>.car</synopsis>
            
            <para>where <literal><emphasis>&lt;module&gt;</emphasis></literal> 
            is the full name of the module, and 
            <literal><emphasis>&lt;version&gt;</emphasis></literal> is the module 
            version identifier. For example:</para>
            
            <screen>ceylon.language-1.0.1.car</screen>
            <screen>org.hibernate-3.0.0.beta.car</screen>
    
            <para>The default module has no version, its module archive name is <literal>default.car</literal></para>
            
            <!--
            <para>Finally, a <emphasis>legacy archive name</emphasis> is of the 
            following standard form:</para>
            
            <synopsis><emphasis>&lt;module&gt;</emphasis>-<emphasis>&lt;version&gt;</emphasis>.jar</synopsis>
            
            <para>For example:</para>
            
            <screen>org.h2-1.2.141.jar</screen>
            -->
            
        </section>
        
        <section id="modulescriptnamesjs">
            <title>Module script names for the JavaScript platform</title>
        
            <para>A <emphasis>module script name</emphasis> is likewise constructed 
            from the module name and version identifier. A module script name is of 
            the following standard form:</para>
            
            <synopsis><emphasis>&lt;module&gt;</emphasis>-<emphasis>&lt;version&gt;</emphasis>.js</synopsis>
            
            <para>where <literal><emphasis>&lt;module&gt;</emphasis></literal> 
            is the full name of the module, and 
            <literal><emphasis>&lt;version&gt;</emphasis></literal> is the module 
            version identifier. For example:</para>
            
            <screen>ceylon.language-1.0.1.js</screen>
            <screen>org.hibernate-3.0.0.beta.js</screen>
    
            <para>The default module has no version, its module archive name is <literal>default.js</literal></para>
    
        </section>
        
        <section id="sourcearchivenames">
            <title>Source archive names</title>
            
            <para>A <emphasis>source archive name</emphasis> is of the following 
            standard form:</para>
            
            <synopsis><emphasis>&lt;module&gt;</emphasis>-<emphasis>&lt;version&gt;</emphasis>.src</synopsis>
            
            <para>For example:</para>
            
            <screen>ceylon.language-1.0.1.src</screen>
            <screen>org.hibernate-3.0.0.beta.src</screen>
    
            <para>The default module has no version, its source archive name is <literal>default.src</literal></para>
            
        </section>
        
        <section id="docarchivenames">
            <title>Documentation archive names</title>
            
            <para>A <emphasis>documentation archive name</emphasis> is of the following 
            standard form:</para>
            
            <synopsis><emphasis>&lt;module&gt;</emphasis>-<emphasis>&lt;version&gt;</emphasis>.zip</synopsis>
            
            <para>For example:</para>
            
            <screen>ceylon.language-1.0.1.zip</screen>
            <screen>org.hibernate-3.0.0.beta.zip</screen>
    
            <para>The default module has no version, its documentation archive name is <literal>default.zip</literal></para>
            
        </section>
        
        <section id="modulearchives">
            <title>Module archives</title>
            
            <para>A Ceylon module archive is a Java <literal>jar</literal>
            archive which:</para>
            
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>contains a Ceylon module descriptor in the
                    <emphasis>module directory</emphasis>,</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>contains the compiled <literal>.class</literal>
                    files for all compilation units belonging to the module, 
                    and</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>has a filename which adheres to the standard for
                    module archive names.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            
            <para>The <emphasis>module directory</emphasis> of the module archive 
            is formed by replacing each period in the fully qualified package name 
            with the directory separator character. For example, the module directory 
            for the module <literal>ceylon.language</literal> is:</para>
            
            <screen>/ceylon/language</screen>
            
            <para>The module directory for the module <literal>org.hibernate</literal> 
            is:</para>
            
            <screen>/org/hibernate</screen>
            
            <para>The <emphasis>package directory</emphasis> for a package 
            belonging to the module archive is formed by replacing each period 
            in the fully qualified package name with the directory separator 
            character. For example, the package directory for the package 
            <literal>org.hibernate.impl</literal> is:</para>
            
            <screen>/org/hibernate/impl</screen>
            
            <para>Inside a module archive, a <literal>.class</literal> file is
            found in the package directory of the package to which it belongs.</para>
            
            <para>Thus, the structure of the module archive for the module
            <literal>org.hello</literal> might be the following:</para>
            
            <screen><![CDATA[org.hello-1.0.0.car
    META-INF/
        MANIFEST.MF
    org/
        hello/
            module.class       //the module descriptor
            main/
                package.class  //a package descriptor
                hello.class
            default/
                DefaultHello.class
            personalized/
                PersonalizedHello.class]]></screen>
                
            <para>A module archive may not contain multiple modules.</para>
            
            <!--comment>
            <para>TODO: should we support the following?</para>
            <para>A module archive may be accompanied by a <emphasis>legacy 
            archive</emphasis>. A legacy archive is a standard Java <literal>jar</literal>
            containing compiled classes required by the module, whose filename 
            adheres to the standard for legacy archive names. At runtime there 
            is no difference between a class packaged in a legacy archive and a 
            class packaged directly in the module archive.</para>
            </comment-->
            
        </section>
        
        <section id="modulescripts">
            <title>Module scripts</title>
            
            <para>A Ceylon module script is a JavaScript source file which:</para>
            
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>complies with the CommonJS Modules specification, 
                    and</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>has a filename which adheres to the standard for
                    module script names.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            
        </section>
        
        <section id="sourcearchives">
            <title>Source archives</title>
            
            <para>A <emphasis>source archive</emphasis> is a <literal>zip</literal> 
            archive which:</para>
            
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>contains the source code (<literal>.ceylon</literal>
                    and <literal>.java</literal> files) for all compilation units 
                    belonging to the module, and</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>has a filename which adheres to the standard for
                    source archive names.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            
            <para>Inside a source archive, a Ceylon or Java source file is located in 
            the <emphasis>package directory</emphasis> of the package to which the 
            compilation unit belongs. The package directory for a package belonging 
            to the source archive is formed by replacing each period in the fully 
            qualified package name with the directory separator character.</para>
            
            <para>Thus, the structure of the source archive for the module
            <literal>org.hello</literal> might be the following:</para>
            
            <screen><![CDATA[org.hello-1.0.0.src
    org/
        hello/
            module.ceylon       //the module descriptor
            main/
                package.ceylon  //a package descriptor
                hello.ceylon
            default/
                DefaultHello.ceylon
            personalized/
                PersonalizedHello.ceylon]]></screen>
            
            <para>A source archive may not contain the source of multiple modules.</para>
            
        </section>
        
        <section id="docarchives">
            <title>Documentation archives</title>
            
            <para>A <emphasis>documentation archive</emphasis> is a <literal>zip</literal> 
            archive which:</para>
            
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>contains the module documentation generated by the documentation
                    compiler (<literal>.html</literal> and resources files), and</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>has a filename which adheres to the standard for
                    documentation archive names.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            
            <para>Inside a documentation archive, HTML source is located in the 
            <literal>module-doc</literal> directory.</para>
            
            <para>Thus, the structure of the documentation archive for the module
            <literal>org.hello</literal> might be the following:</para>
            
            <screen><![CDATA[org.hello-1.0.0.zip
    module-doc/
        .resources/
            ...
        index.html
        search.html
        module.ceylon.html
        main/
            index.html
            package.ceylon.html
            hello.ceylon.html
        default/
            index.html
            DefaultHello.html
            DefaultHello.ceylon.html
        personalized/
            index.html
            PersonalizedHello.html
            PersonalizedHello.ceylon.html]]></screen>
            
            <para>A documentation archive may not contain the documentation of multiple 
            modules.</para>
            
        </section>
        
        <section id="modulerepositories">
            <title>Module repositories</title>
            
            <para>A module repository is a directory structure on the local
            filesystem or a remote HTTP server.</para>
            
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>A <emphasis>local</emphasis> module repository is 
                    identified by a filesystem path.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem> 
                    <para>A <emphasis>remote</emphasis> module repository is 
                    identified by a URL with protocol <literal>http:</literal> 
                    or <literal>https:</literal>.</para> 
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            
            <para>A <emphasis>publishable</emphasis> module repository is a local
            module repository, or a WebDAV-enabled remote module repository.</para>
            
            <para>For example:</para>
            
            <screen>modules</screen>
            <screen>/usr/bin/ceylon/modules</screen>
            <screen>http://jboss.org/ceylon/modules</screen>
            <screen>https://gavin:secret@modules.ceylon-lang.org</screen>
            
            <para>A module repository contains module archives, module scripts, 
            source archives, and documentation archives. The address of an artifact 
            belonging to the repository adheres to the following standard form:</para>
            
            <synopsis><emphasis>&lt;repository&gt;</emphasis>/<emphasis>&lt;module-path&gt;</emphasis>/<emphasis>&lt;version&gt;</emphasis>/<emphasis>&lt;artifact&gt;</emphasis></synopsis>
            
            <para>where <literal><emphasis>&lt;repository&gt;</emphasis></literal> 
            is the filesystem path or URL of the repository,
            <literal><emphasis>&lt;artifact&gt;</emphasis></literal> is the name
            of the artifact, <literal><emphasis>&lt;version&gt;</emphasis></literal>
            is the module version, and <literal><emphasis>&lt;module-path&gt;</emphasis></literal> 
            is formed by replacing every period with a slash in the module name.</para>
    
            <para>The default module having no version, its access path does not 
            contain the version.</para>
    
            <synopsis><emphasis>&lt;repository&gt;</emphasis>/default/<emphasis>&lt;archive&gt;</emphasis></synopsis>
            
            <para>For example, the module archive <literal>ceylon.language-1.0.1.car</literal>,
            module script, source archive <literal>ceylon.language-1.0.1.src</literal>,
            and documentation archive belonging to the repository included in the Ceylon SDK are
            obtained from the following addresses:</para>
     
            <screen>modules/ceylon/language/1.0.1/ceylon.language-1.0.1.car</screen>        
            <screen>modules/ceylon/language/1.0.1/ceylon.language-1.0.1.js</screen>
            <screen>modules/ceylon/language/1.0.1/ceylon.language-1.0.1.src</screen>
            <screen>modules/ceylon/language/1.0.1/ceylon.language-1.0.1.zip</screen>
            
            <para>The module archive <literal>org.hibernate-3.0.0.beta.car</literal>,
            source archive <literal>org.hibernate-3.0.0.beta.src</literal>, and 
            documentation archive belonging to the repository 
            <literal>http://jboss.org/ceylon/modules</literal> are obtained from the 
            following addresses:</para>
            
            <screen>http://jboss.org/ceylon/modules/org/hibernate/3.0.0.beta/org.hibernate-3.0.0.beta.car</screen>
            <screen>http://jboss.org/ceylon/modules/org/hibernate/3.0.0.beta/org.hibernate-3.0.0.beta.src</screen>
            <screen>http://jboss.org/ceylon/modules/org/hibernate/3.0.0.beta/org.hibernate-3.0.0.beta.zip</screen>
            
            <para>The module archive <literal>org.h2-1.2.141.car</literal> and legacy 
            archive <literal>org.h2-1.2.141.jar</literal> belonging to the repository 
            <literal>/usr/bin/ceylon/modules</literal> are obtained from the following 
            addresses:</para>
            
            <screen>/usr/bin/ceylon/modules/org/h2/1.2.141/org.h2-1.2.141.car</screen>
            <screen>/usr/bin/ceylon/modules/org/h2/1.2.141/org.h2-1.2.141.jar</screen>
            
            <para>For each archive, the module repository may contain a SHA-1 checksum 
            file. The checksum file is a plain text file containing just the SHA-1 checksum
            of the archive. The address of a checksum file adheres to the following standard 
            form:</para>
            
            <synopsis><emphasis>&lt;repository&gt;</emphasis>/<emphasis>&lt;module-path&gt;</emphasis>/<emphasis>&lt;version&gt;</emphasis>/<emphasis>&lt;archive&gt;</emphasis>.sha1</synopsis>
            
            <para>The compiler or module runtime verifies the checksum after downloading
            the archive from the module repository.</para>
            
            <para>A module repository may contain documentation generated by the Ceylon
            documentation compiler in exploded form. A module's documentation resides in the
            <emphasis>module documentation directory</emphasis>, a directory with address 
            adhering to the following standard form:</para>
            
            <synopsis><emphasis>&lt;repository&gt;</emphasis>/<emphasis>&lt;module-path&gt;</emphasis>/<emphasis>&lt;version&gt;</emphasis>/module-doc/</synopsis>
            
            <para>For example, the home page for the documentation of the module
            <literal>org.hibernate</literal> is:</para>
            
            <screen>http://jboss.org/ceylon/modules/org/hibernate/module-doc/index.html</screen>
                    
        </section>
        
        <section id="packagedescriptors">
            <title>Package descriptors</title>
            
            <para>A <emphasis>package descriptor</emphasis> is defined in a source file
            named <literal>package.ceylon</literal> in the package it describes.</para>
            
            <synopsis>PackageDescriptor: Annotations "package" FullPackageName ";"</synopsis>
            
            <para>A <literal>package</literal> may be annotated <literal>shared</literal>. 
            A <literal>shared</literal> package is visible outside the containing module,
            that is, in any module which imports the containing module.</para>
            
            <para>The package descriptor is optional for unshared packages.</para>
            
            <programlisting>"The typesafe query API."
license "http://www.gnu.org/licenses/lgpl.html"
shared package org.hibernate.query;</programlisting>
    
        </section>
            
        <section id="moduledescriptors">
            <title>Module descriptors</title>
            
            <para>A <emphasis>module descriptor</emphasis> is defined in a source file
            named <literal>module.ceylon</literal> in the root package of the module it
            describes (the package with the same name as the module).</para>
            
            <!--para>A module may be <emphasis>runnable</emphasis>. The module descriptor
            for a runnable module specifies an <emphasis>entry point</emphasis>, a 
            toplevel method or class with no parameters.</para-->
            
            <synopsis>ModuleDescriptor: Annotations "module" FullPackageName StringLiteral ModuleBody</synopsis>
            
            <para>The literal string after the module name specifies the version of the
            module.</para>
            
            <para>A module may import other modules.</para>
            
            <synopsis>ModuleBody: "{" ModuleImport* "}"</synopsis>
            <synopsis>ModuleImport: Annotations "import" (FullPackageName|StringLiteral) StringLiteral ";"</synopsis>
            
            <para>The name of the imported module may be specified using the usual syntax
            for a module name, or as a literal string, to allow interoperation with
            legacy module repositories existing outside the Ceylon ecosystem.</para>
            
            <comment><para>Note: this enables interoperation with Maven.</para></comment>
            
            <comment><para>Note: in Ceylon 1.0 it is illegal to explicitly import the
            module <literal>ceylon.language</literal>. The language module is always
            implicitly imported.</para></comment>
            
            <para>The string literal after the imported module name specifies the version 
            of the imported module.</para>
            
            <para>An imported module may be annotated <literal>optional</literal> and/or
            <literal>shared</literal>.</para>
            
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>If module <literal>x</literal> has a <literal>shared</literal> 
                    import of module <literal>y</literal>, then any module that imports
                    <literal>x</literal> implicitly imports <literal>y</literal>.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>If module <literal>x</literal> has an <literal>optional</literal>
                    import of module <literal>y</literal>, then <literal>x</literal> may
                    be executed even if <literal>y</literal> is not available at runtime.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            
            <para>If a declaration belonging to module <literal>x</literal> is visible 
            outside the module and involves types imported from a different module
            <literal>y</literal>, then the module import of <literal>y</literal> in the
            module descriptor for <literal>x</literal> must be <literal>shared</literal>.</para>
            
            <programlisting>"The best-ever ORM solution!"
license "http://www.gnu.org/licenses/lgpl.html"
module org.hibernate "3.0.0.beta" {
    shared import ceylon.language "1.0.1";
    import javax.sql "4.0";
}</programlisting>
            
            <programlisting>"The test suite for Hibernate"
license "http://www.gnu.org/licenses/lgpl.html"
module org.hibernate.test "3.0.0.beta" {
    import org.hibernate "3.0.0.beta";
    TestSuite().run();
}</programlisting>
            
            <comment><para>TODO: do we allow procedural code in the body of a 
            <literal>module</literal>?</para></comment>
            
        </section>
    
    </section>

<!--section id="tools">
    <title>Toolset</title>

    <para>The Ceylon SDK contains the following tools:</para>
    
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para>the Java VM, <literal>java</literal>,</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>the front end for the Java VM, <literal>ceylon</literal>,</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>the compiler, <literal>ceylonc</literal>,</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>the module info tool, <literal>ceylonp</literal>,</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>the documentation compiler, <literal>ceylond</literal>,</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>the repository replicator, <literal>ceylonr</literal>, and</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>the source archive extractor, <literal>ceylonf</literal>.</para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    
    <section id="sourcedirectories">
        <title>Source directories</title>
        
        <para>A <emphasis>source directory</emphasis> contains Ceylon source 
        code in files with the extension <literal>.ceylon</literal> and Java 
        source code in files with the extension <literal>.java</literal>. 
        The module and package to which a compilation unit belongs is 
        determined by the subdirectory in which the source file is found.</para>
        
        <para>The name of the package to which a compilation unit belongs is 
        formed by replacing every path directory separator character with a 
        period in the relative path from the source directory to the 
        subdirectory containing the source file. In the case of a Java source 
        file, the subdirectory must agree with the package specified by the 
        Java <literal>package</literal> declaration.</para>
        
        <para>The name of the module to which a compilation unit belongs is 
        determined by searching all containing directories for a module 
        descriptor. The name of the module is formed by replacing every path
        directory separator character with a period in the relative path 
        from the source directory to the subdirectory containing the module 
        descriptor.</para>
        
        <para>Thus, the structure of the source directory containing the module
        <literal>org.hello</literal> might be the following:</para>
        
        <programlisting><![CDATA[source/
    org/
        hello/
            module.ceylon      //the module descriptor
            main/
                hello.ceylon
            default/
                DefaultHello.ceylon
            personalized/
                PersonalizedHello.ceylon]]></programlisting>
                
        <para>The source code for multiple modules may be contained in a
        single source directory.</para>
        
    </section>
    
    <section id="identifyingversionedmodules">
        <title>Identifying versioned modules</title>
        
        <para>The command line tools expect the following format for a versioned
        module name:</para>
        
        <programlisting><emphasis>&lt;module&gt;</emphasis>/<emphasis>&lt;version&gt;</emphasis></programlisting>
        
        <para>where <literal><emphasis>&lt;module&gt;</emphasis></literal> 
        is the full name of the module, and 
        <literal><emphasis>&lt;version&gt;</emphasis></literal> is the module 
        version identifier. For example:</para>
        
        <programlisting>ceylon.language/1.0.1</programlisting>
        <programlisting>org.h2/1.2.141</programlisting>
                
    </section>
    
    <section id="vmfrontend">
        <title>The VM front end</title>
        
        <para>The <literal>ceylon</literal> command accepts the name of a 
        module with an optional version, along with the following options:</para>
        
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para><literal>-run</literal> specifies the fully 
                qualified name of a toplevel method or class with 
                no parameters.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><literal>-rep</literal> specifies a module
                repository.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><literal>-src</literal> specifies a source
                directory.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><literal>-d</literal> disables the default
                module repositories and source directory.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><literal>-help</literal> displays a usage
                help page.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><literal>-version</literal> specifies the
                Ceylon version.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        
        <para>The <literal>ceylon</literal> options must come first,
        before the module name and version. Any argument passed after
        the module name and version will be passed to the Ceylon
        module that we are running.</para>
        
        <para>The default module repositories are <literal>modules</literal>
        and <literal>http://modules.ceylon-lang.org</literal>,
        and the default source directory is <literal>source</literal>.</para>
        
        <programlisting>ceylon -rep http://jboss.org/ceylon/modules \
        -src ~/projects/hibernate/src \
        org.hibernate.test/3.0.0.beta -hibernate-arg</programlisting>
               
        <para>Execution begins with the named toplevel method or class, or
        with the entry point specified in the module descriptor, and imported 
        modules are loaded lazily as classes they contain are needed. The 
        name and version id of the imported module containing the needed 
        class are determined from the imported package name specified by
        the compilation unit and the imported module version specified by 
        the module descriptor.</para>
                
        <para>Each version of each module is loaded using a different class 
        loader. Classes inside a module have access to other classes in the 
        same module and to classes belonging to modules that are explicitly 
        imported in the module descriptor. Classes in other modules are not 
        accessible.</para>
        
        <para>The module runtime searches for modules in the following 
        locations:</para>
        
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>module archives in the specified repositories,</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>source archives in the specified repositories, 
                and</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>module directories in the specified source 
                directories.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        
        <para>If no version identifier is specified for a module, the module 
        is assumed to exist in a source directory.</para>
        
        <para>Source code in source archives and source directories is 
        automatically compiled by the module runtime.</para>
                
    </section>

    <section id="compiler">
        <title>The compiler</title>
        
        <para>The Ceylon compiler is able to compile Ceylon and Java source 
        code and directly produce module and source archives in a module 
        repository.</para>
        
        <para>The <literal>ceylonc</literal> command accepts a list of
        module names (without versions) or file paths, along with the 
        following options:</para>
        
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para><literal>-out</literal> specifies the output module 
                repository (which must be publishable).</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><literal>-src</literal> specifies a source
                directory.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><literal>-rep</literal> specifies a module
                repository containing dependencies.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><literal>-d</literal> disables the default
                module repositories and source directory.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><literal>-user</literal> sets the user name
                for the HTTP output repository.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><literal>-pass</literal> sets the password
                for the HTTP output repository.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><literal>-help</literal> displays a usage
                help page.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><literal>-version</literal> specifies the
                Ceylon version.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        
        <para>The default module repositories are <literal>modules</literal>
        and <literal>http://modules.ceylon-lang.org</literal>,
        and the default source directory is <literal>source</literal>.
        The default output module repository is <literal>modules</literal>.</para>
        
        <programlisting>ceylonc org.hibernate.test org.hibernate \
        -rep http://jboss.org/ceylon/modules \
        -src ~/projects/hibernate/src \
        -out ~/projects/hibernate/build</programlisting>
        
        <comment><para>TODO: how do you create signed jars? Some additional
        commandline options?</para></comment>
        
        <para>The compiler searches for compilation units belonging to the 
        specified modules in the specified source directories. For each 
        specified module, the compiler generates a module archive, source 
        archive, and their checksum files in the specified output module 
        repository.</para>
        
        <para>All program elements imported by a compilation unit must
        belong to the same module as the compilation unit, or must belong
        to a module that is explicitly imported in the module descriptor.</para>
        
        <para>The compiler searches for dependencies in the following 
        locations:</para>
        
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>module archives in the specified repositories,</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>source archives in the specified repositories, 
                and</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>module directories in the specified source 
                directories.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
                
    </section>
    
    <section id="moduleinfotool">
        <title>The module info tool</title>
        
        <para>The module info tool prints information about the contents of
        a module archive, its description, its licence, and its dependencies
        to the console.</para>
        
        <para>The <literal>ceylonp</literal> command accepts a list of module 
        names with optional versions, along with the following options:</para>
        
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para><literal>-rep</literal> specifies a module
                repository.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><literal>-src</literal> specifies a source
                directory.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><literal>-d</literal> disables the default
                module repositories and source directory.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        
        <para>The default module repositories are <literal>modules</literal>
        and <literal>http://modules.ceylon-lang.org</literal>,
        and the default source directory is <literal>source</literal>.</para>
        
        <programlisting>ceylonp org.hibernate/3.0.0.beta
        -rep http://jboss.org/ceylon/modules</programlisting>
        
        <para>The tool searches for modules in the following locations:</para>
        
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>module archives in the specified repositories,</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>source archives in the specified repositories, 
                and</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>module directories in the specified source 
                directories.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        
        <para>If no version identifier is specified for a module, the tool 
        prints information about all available versions of the module.</para>

    </section>
        
    <section id="documentationcompiler">
        <title>The documentation compiler</title>
        
        <para>The documentation compiler generates XHTML-format documentation 
        from Ceylon source files. The content of the <literal>doc</literal>
        annotations is treated as Markdown format text.</para>
        
        <para>The <literal>ceylond</literal> command accepts a list of
        module names with optional versions, along with the following options:</para>
        
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para><literal>-out</literal> specifies the output module 
                repository (which must be publishable).</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><literal>-src</literal> specifies a source
                directory.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><literal>-rep</literal> specifies a module
                repository containing source archives.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><literal>-non-shared</literal> includes documentation
                for package-private declarations.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><literal>-source-code</literal> includes source 
                code in the generated documentation.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><literal>-d</literal> disables the default module 
                repositories and source directory.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><literal>-user</literal> sets the user name
                for the HTTP output repository.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><literal>-pass</literal> sets the password
                for the HTTP output repository.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><literal>-help</literal> displays a usage
                help page.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><literal>-version</literal> specifies the
                Ceylon version.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        
        <para>The default module repositories are <literal>modules</literal>
        and <literal>http://modules.ceylon-lang.org</literal>,
        and the default source directory is <literal>source</literal>.
        The default output module repository is <literal>modules</literal>.</para>
        
        <programlisting>ceylond org.hibernate/3.0.0.beta \
        -src ~/projects/hibernate/src \
        -out ~/projects/hibernate/build</programlisting>
        
        <para>The documentation compiler searches for compilation units 
        belonging to the specified modules in the specified source directories
        and in source archives in the specified module repositories. For each 
        specified module, the compiler generates a set of XHTML pages in the 
        module documentation directory (the <literal>module-doc</literal> 
        directory) of the specified output module repository.</para>
        
        <para>The compiler searches for source in the following locations:</para>
        
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>source archives in the specified repositories, 
                and</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>module directories in the specified source 
                directories.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
                
        <para>If no version identifier is specified for a module, the module 
        is assumed to exist in a source directory.</para>
                
    </section>
    
    <section id="repositoryreplicator">
        <title>The repository replicator</title>
        
        <para>The repository replicator copies modules from one repository
        to another. For example, it may be used to create local copies of
        modules in remote repositories, or to publish modules to a remote 
        repository.</para>
        
        <para>To publish a module to <literal>http://modules.ceylon-lang.org</literal>,
        a module developer may use the repository replicator to submit the
        module via WebDAV.</para>
        
        <para>The <literal>ceylonr</literal> command accepts a list of 
        versioned module names, along with the following options:</para>
        
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para><literal>-out</literal> specifies the output module 
                repository (which must be publishable).</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><literal>-rep</literal> specifies a module
                repository containing source archives.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><literal>-d</literal> disables the default
                module repositories.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><literal>-nosrc</literal> disables replication of
                source archives.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><literal>-nodoc</literal> disables replication of
                module documentation directories.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        
        <para>The default module repositories are <literal>modules</literal>
        and <literal>http://modules.ceylon-lang.org</literal>. The default output
        module repository is <literal>modules</literal>.</para>
        
        <programlisting>ceylonr org.hibernate/3.0.0.beta org.hibernate.test/3.0.0.beta org.hibernate.example/3.0.0.beta \
        -rep http://jboss.org/ceylon/modules</programlisting>
        
        <programlisting>ceylonr org.hibernate/3.0.0.beta \
        -rep modules \
        -out https://gavin:secret@modules.ceylon-lang.org</programlisting>
        
        <para>The repository replicator searches for directories containing
        the specified modules in the specified module repositories and, if 
        found, replicates their contents into the specified output module 
        repository.</para>
        
    </section>
    
    <section id="sourcearchiveextractor">
        <title>The source archive extractor</title>
        
        <para>The source archive extractor fetches source archives and 
        extracts their contents into a source directory. This is
        especially useful for working with example projects.</para>
        
        <para>The <literal>ceylonf</literal> command accepts a list of
        versioned module names, along with the following options:</para>
        
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para><literal>-src</literal> specifies the output source
                directory.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><literal>-rep</literal> specifies a module
                repository containing source archives.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><literal>-d</literal> disables the default
                module repositories.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        
        <para>The default module repositories are <literal>modules</literal>
        and <literal>http://modules.ceylon-lang.org</literal>. The default output 
        source directory is <literal>source</literal>.</para>
        
        <programlisting>ceylonf org.hibernate.example/3.0.0.beta \
        -rep http://jboss.org/ceylon/modules \
        -src ~/projects/hibernate/src</programlisting>
        
        <para>The source archive extractor searches for source archives for
        the specified modules in the specified module repositories and, if
        found, extracts their contents into the specified source directory.</para>
        
    </section>

    <section id="jarimporter">
        <title>The JAR importer</title>
        
        <para>The JAR import allows you to publish a Java JAR into
        a Ceylon repository so they can then be imported by Ceylon
        modules. This is very useful for interoperating with
        Java libraries.</para>
        
        <para>The <literal>ceylon-import-jar</literal> command accepts a module
        name and version and a JAR file path, along with the following options:</para>
        
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para><literal>-out</literal> specifies the output module 
                repository (which must be publishable).</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><literal>-d</literal> disables the default
                module repositories.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><literal>-user</literal> sets the user name
                for the HTTP output repository.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><literal>-pass</literal> sets the password
                for the HTTP output repository.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><literal>-help</literal> displays a usage
                help page.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><literal>-version</literal> specifies the
                Ceylon version.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><literal>-debug</literal> prints debugging
                information.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        
        <para>The default output module repository is <literal>modules</literal>.</para>
        
        <programlisting>ceylon-import-jar org.hibernate.example/3.0.0.beta \
        path/to/hibernate.jar \
        -out ~/.ceylon/repo</programlisting>
        
        <para>The JAR importer imports a Java JAR as a Ceylon module into a Ceylon
        repository, so that it can by imported by Ceylon modules.</para>
        
    </section>

</section-->

</chapter>